<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-boucadair-dnsop-prefix64" ipr="trust200902"
     updates="6147">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="PREFIX64 in DNS Messages">An EDNS0 Option for Sharing
    Pref64::/n</title>

    <author fullname="Mohamed Boucadair" initials="M." surname="Boucadair">
      <organization>Orange</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>

          <city>Rennes</city>

          <region></region>

          <code>35000</code>

          <country>France</country>
        </postal>

        <email>mohamed.boucadair@orange.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date />

    <abstract>
      <t>This document specifies an Extension Mechanisms for DNS (EDNS0)
      option to convey the IPv6 prefix used to build IPv4-converted IPv6
      addresses. When conveyed in a DNS query, the option communicates the
      IPv6 prefix used in the network from which the query was originated.
      Such a network is assumed to enable a Network Address and Protocol
      Translation from IPv6 clients to IPv4 servers (NAT64) function.
      DNS64-capable servers will use that prefix to build synthesized AAAA
      records, rather than relying on a preconfigured prefix. When conveyed in
      a DNS reply, the option conveys the IPv6 prefix that is used by a
      DNS64-capable server to synthesized AAAA records. Such information helps
      to automatically detect mismatches between the local NAT64 configuration
      and the one enforced at the DNS64 server. Also, security-aware and
      validating hosts may use the new EDNS0 option to signal the presence of
      a NAT64 function. That signal is used by the DNS server to fill the
      additional section of the AAAA reply in order to supply A RRs of the
      target. Dual queries and delays are thus avoided.</t>

      <t>This document updates RFC 6147.<!--
--></t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>Network Address and Protocol Translation from IPv6 clients to IPv4
      servers (NAT64) function <xref target="RFC6146"></xref> is widely
      deployed, especially in cellular networks. Such a function is solicited
      when an IPv6-only host communicates with an IPv4-only server. For that
      communication to take place, IPv4-only servers are represented in the
      IPv6 domain by synthesizing IPv6 addresses based on IPv4 addresses
      (called, IPv4-converted IPv6 addresses). The address translation
      algorithm is specified in <xref target="RFC6052"></xref>. In addition to
      an IPv4 address, this algorithm uses a dedicated IPv6 prefix as input.
      Such a prefix can be the Well-Known Prefix (i.e., 64:ff9b::/96) or a
      Network-Specific Prefix (NSP).</t>

      <t>DNS64 <xref target="RFC6147"></xref> specifies a companion mechanism
      to represent IPv4-only servers in the IPv6 domains. Such a mechanism
      relies upon the same address translation algorithm as the one used by
      the NAT64 function. When both DNS64 and NAT64 are deployed in the same
      network, the same IPv6 prefix must be used to feed the address
      translation algorithm (Section 2 of <xref target="RFC6147"></xref>). A
      sample deployment scenario is depicted in <xref target="sample"></xref>.
      Note that no mechanism is supported to synchronize the prefix configured
      in both functions. In particular, there is no communication between the
      DNS64 and NAT64 functions.</t>

      <t><figure align="center" anchor="sample"
          title="Sample Deployment (RFC6146)">
          <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[+---------------------+         +---------------+
|IPv6 network         |         |    IPv4       |
|           |  +-------------+  |  network      |
|           |--| Name server |--|               |
|           |  | with DNS64  |  |  +----+       |
|  +----+   |  +-------------+  |  | H2 |       |
|  | H1 |---|         |         |  +----+       |
|  +----+   |      +-------+    |  192.0.2.1    |
|2001:db8::1|------| NAT64 |----|               |
|           |      +-------+    |               |
|           |         |         |               |
+---------------------+         +---------------+]]></artwork>
        </figure></t>

      <t>In networks where DNS64 is enabled, some deployments use distinct IP
      addresses to reach the "normal" DNS server and the DNS64 server. This is
      used to demux queries issues by IPv6-only hosts from those from
      dual-stack hosts. The mechanism defined in this document allows to use
      the same DNS configuration for both IPv6-only and dual-stack hosts.</t>

      <t>NAT64 does not require a DNS64 server to be enabled and, even if it
      is used, it does not mandate that it is enabled in the same network. As
      such, several public DNS64 servers are currently available for use over
      the Internet. However, these servers are restricted to the Well-Known
      Prefix. Users who decides to bypass their network-provisioned DNS64
      server (e.g., including both trusted (access network, typically) and
      untrusted networks such as Airports) may experience connectivity issues
      if an NSP is used in their local networks (Section 4.4 of <xref
      target="RFC8683"></xref>). This document solves that issues by
      specifying a mechanism that allows to use any DNS64 server, not only the
      one hosted in the network that enables the NAT64.</t>

      <t>If the IPv4 address of a remote IPv4-only server is known to an
      IPv6-only host (e.g., IPv4 literals, legacy DNS), the IPv6-only host can
      proceed with local address synthesis. For example, the stub resolver on
      the IPv6-only host tries to obtain (native) AAAA records, and if they
      are not found, the DNS64 function on the host will send a query for A
      records and then synthesize AAAA records. This behavior requires the
      host's stub-resolver to learn the prefix used for IPv6/IPv4 translation
      and synthesize AAAA records accordingly. Many mechanisms were specified
      to discover such prefix, e.g.:<list style="symbols">
          <t><xref target="RFC7225"></xref> defines a new Port Control
          Protocol (PCP) option <xref target="RFC6887"></xref> to inform hosts
          about the Pref64::/n and suffix used by a NAT64 function.</t>

          <t><xref target="RFC8781"></xref> specifies a Neighbor Discovery
          option used in Router Advertisements (RAs) to communicate NAT64
          prefixes to hosts.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>The reader may refer to <xref target="RFC7050"></xref><xref
      target="RFC7051"></xref> for an analysis on the issues related to the
      discovery of the Pref64::/n.</t>

      <t>In some environments two DNS queries are issued even if the host is
      serviced using an IPv6-only connectivity (typically, AAAA followed by
      A). These two queries are sent sequentially, which introduces an extra
      delay when the target resource is IPv4-only. Such delay can be prevented
      owing to the mechanism specified in this document. As a side effect, the
      mechanism optimizes the load on DNS64 servers as only one query will be
      used instead of two.</t>

      <t>This document updates <xref target="RFC6146"></xref> as it extends
      the DNS64 processing to also consider the supplied Pref64::/n in an
      EDNS0 option to synthesize AAA records. In particular statements such as
      "locally configured Pref64::/n" are updated to "locally configured
      Pref64::/n or Pref64::/n supplied in an EDNS0 PREFIX64 option". To that
      aim, this document leverages the aforementioned discovery mechanism to
      detect the presence of a NAT64 function.</t>

      <t>In summary, the mechanism defined in this document is meant to:</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>Provide a signal to indicate the support of NAT64 in a
          network.</t>

          <t>Allow a DNS64 server to service clients with distinct NAT64
          prefixes.</t>

          <t>Avoid delays when both A and AAA queries are required.</t>

          <t>Optimize load on DNS server as only one query is generated rather
          that duplicating load when both AAA and A queries are required.</t>
        </list></t>
    </section>

    <section title="Terminology">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and
      "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in BCP 14
      <xref target="RFC2119"></xref><xref target="RFC8174"></xref> when, and
      only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.</t>

      <t>The reader should be familiar with terms and concepts defined in
      <xref target="RFC6052"></xref>, <xref target="RFC6146"></xref>, and
      <xref target="RFC6147"></xref>. Also, the document makes use of terms
      defined in <xref target="RFC8499"></xref>.</t>

      <t>"IPv6-only host" refers to a host with an IPv6-only connectivity.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Option Format">
      <t>The format of the PREFIX64 EDNS0 option is shown in <xref
      target="edns0"></xref>. This format adheres to the guidelines specified
      in Section 6.1.2 of <xref target="RFC6891"></xref>.</t>

      <t><figure align="center" anchor="edns0"
          title="PREFIX64 EDNS0 Option Format">
          <artwork><![CDATA[               +0 (MSB)                            +1 (LSB)
    +---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+
 0: |                          OPTION-CODE                          |
    +---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+
 2: |                         OPTION-LENGTH                         |
    +---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+
 4: |                                                               |
    /                          PREFIX64                             /
    /                                                               /
    +---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+

]]></artwork>
        </figure></t>

      <t>The description of the fields is as follows:</t>

      <t><list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="OPTION-CODE:">MUST be set to TBA (<xref
          target="IANA"></xref>).</t>

          <t hangText="OPTION-LENGTH:">Size (in octets) of the enclosed
          Pref64::/n. Allowed values are: 0, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, and 9. <vspace
          blankLines="1" />The receiver MUST ignore the option if the
          OPTION-LENGTH is not set to one of those values. <vspace
          blankLines="1" />When the value is set to 0, this indicates the
          presence of a NAT64 function in the network from which the query is
          generated.</t>

          <t hangText="PREFIX64:">This field identifies the IPv6 unicast
          prefix to be used for constructing an IPv4-converted IPv6 address
          from an IPv4 address as specified in Section 2.2 of <xref
          target="RFC6052"></xref>. In such case, the prefix length MUST be
          32, 40, 48, 56, 64, and 96 bits (i.e., OPTION-LENGTH must be set to
          4, 5, 6, 7, 8, and 9) as specified in <xref
          target="RFC6052"></xref>. <vspace blankLines="1" />This prefix can
          be the Well-Known Prefix (i.e., 64:ff9b::/96) or a Network-Specific
          Prefix. <vspace blankLines="1" />The address synthesis MUST follow
          the guidelines documented in <xref target="RFC6052"></xref>.</t>
        </list></t>
    </section>

    <section title="Protocol Description">
      <t>A stub-resolver on an IPv6-only host that discovers the presence of
      NAT64 inserts the PREFIX64 EDNS0 option in its AAAA queries. If the
      stub-resolver is on a multi-interfaced device, the Pref64::/n conveyed
      in the PREFIX64 EDNS0 option MUST be the one that is associated with the
      interface over which the DNS query is sent.</t>

      <t>A stub-resolver that is prepared to handle A RRs enclosed in the
      additional section (e.g., security-aware and validating hosts) MAY
      insert a PREFIX64 EDNS0 option with an OPTION-LENGTH set to zero in its
      AAAA DNS queries. Such option is used by intermediate/authoritative
      servers as a signal to include A RR in the additional section.</t>

      <t>If a DNS server enables a DNS64 function, then the AAAA query is
      treated as in <xref target="RFC6147"></xref> with the exception that
      supplied valid Pref64::/n are used for synthesizing AAAA records. The
      reply MAY echo the PREFIX64 EDNS0 option.</t>

      <t>A DNS forwarder MAY be configured to forward AAAA queries that carry
      an PREFIX64 EDNS0 option with non-null prefixes to a DNS64 server. Such
      queries are thus relayed to that DNS64 server. Upon receipt of such
      queries, the AAAA query is treated as in <xref target="RFC6147"></xref>
      with the exception that supplied valid Pref64::/n are used for
      synthesizing AAAA records. This prevents from exposing distinct IP
      addresses of DNS servers for "normal" DNS and DNS64 operations.</t>

      <t>A DNS64 MAY be instructed to return the Pref64::/n that it uses when
      synthesizing AAAA records. If so, the DNS64 MUST include the PREFIX64
      option in its replies that carry synthesized AAAA records. This is
      superior to the current situation where users have to check the
      documentation (when available) to determine the prefix used by a DNS64
      server for address synthesis. Absent such checks, errors can be
      encountered to service IPv6-only hosts. The use of PREFIX64 option
      allows to automatically detect mismatches between the prefix used in the
      network (that is, the NAT64 function) and the one that is used by a
      DNS64 function.</t>

      <t>A stub-resolver SHOULD determine whether the returned AAAA includes a
      native or IPv4-converted IPv6 by comparing the first bits of the IPv6
      address with the local Pref64::/n. This check is also meant to determine
      that an on-path attacker modifying the PREFIX64 option.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>Generic EDNS0 security considerations are discussed in Section 8 of
      <xref target="RFC6891"></xref>.</t>

      <t>As discussed in Section 5.5 of <xref target="RFC6147"></xref>, a
      security-aware and validating host has to perform the DNS64 function
      locally. This specification does not prevent that. The only enhancement
      is the receipt of A RRs in the additional section of AAAA replies.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This document requests IANA to assign the following new code from the
      "DNS EDNS0 Option Codes (OPT)" registry available at <xref
      target="DNS-OPT"></xref>:</t>

      <t><figure align="center">
          <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[Value      Name          Status        Reference
-----      --------      --------      -------------
TBA        PREFIX64      Standard      [ThisDocument]
]]></artwork>
        </figure></t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>Thanks to Tiru Reddy for the comments.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8174'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6891'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6052'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6146'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6147'?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.7225'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.7051'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.7050'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8781'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8499'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6887'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8683'?>

      <reference anchor="DNS-OPT"
                 target="http://www.iana.org/assignments/dns-parameters/dns-parameters.xhtml#dns-parameters-11">
        <front>
          <title>DNS EDNS0 Option Codes (OPT)</title>

          <author fullname="IANA">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date />
        </front>
      </reference>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
